Guide to the William Wallace Booth Papers, 1922-1973 AIS.1973.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- University of Pittsburgh, 1922-1973; 1941-1968; 1.
  - Committees of the Board of Trustees, 1940-1973; III.
    - Finance Committees, 4.
      - Subject files - "Observations on Investment Policies for Endowment Funds" and "Policies and Procedures of the Investment Committee of the Board of Trustees" (Box 7, Folder 100)
      - Planning and Development Committee correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 7, Folder 101)
        This correspondence announces the initial meeting of the committee appointed to solicit funds from public donors for building program; the remainder of this correspondence is address to committee member William Wallace Booth and contains information concerning the mechanics, functions, activities, and objectives of the committee.
      - Planning and Development Committee - Minutes, 1961, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 102)
      - Planning and Development Committee - Subject files, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 103)
        Letters of solicitation and acknowledgment of contributions from: Frank Mesta, E.S. Taylor, and Eisaman, December 1951 Notes gifts of stock from William Wallace Booth to the Building Fund
    - Physical Plant and Site Development Committee, 5.
      - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 104)
        A letter transmitting two reports: "Definition of a University Health Center" and recommendations of the "Special Study Committee of the Health Center" a letter of transmittal forwarding lists of the boards of trustees of Presbyterian, Women's, Children's, and Eye and Ear Hospitals; Child Guidance Center; and the Central Blood Bank.
      - Memoranda, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 105)
        A memorandum of understanding between the University and the Pittsburgh Catholic Diocese that the property opposite Catholic Cathedral will be used only for banking or University purposes (Marked Confidential).
      - Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 106)
      - Minutes, 1959-1967 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Property Committee, 6.
      - Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 7, Folder 108)
        Correspondence regarding moving of Logan Armory to the North Side, July 23, 1951 and August 8, 1951; letter transmitting minutes of the meeting with the URA concerning acquisition of property for the Graduate School of Public Health and the Athletic Department, January 27, 1953; Booth notified of his appointment to chair the Property Committee, July 14, 1952.
      - Memoranda, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 109)
        From the Athletic Director, recommendation for acquisition of property to provide adequate athletic facilities.
      - Minutes, 1951, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 110)
      - Reports - Building progress and construction account reports, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 111)
      - Reports - Building progress and construction account reports, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 112)
      - Reports - Building progress and construction account reports, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 113)
      - Reports - Building progress and construction account reports, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 114)
      - Reports - Building progress and construction account reports, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Special Committees of the Board of Trustees, 1955-1969; IV.
    - Complete the Cathedral Committee, 1.
      - Correspondence, April-May 1934 (Box 7, Folder 116)
        Letters to William Wallace Booth, first thanking him for his efforts on behalf of the committee then outlining its purpose and activities.
      - Memoranda (Box 7, Folder 117)
        Facts concerning financing, construction, and future use of the Cathedral to be presented to the Masonic Fund Society; instruction to campaign workers.
    - Financial Development Committee, 2.
      - Minutes, January 4, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - R.H. Fitzgerald Dinner Committee, 3.
      In honor of his retirement as chancellor.
      - Correspondence, May 12, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 119)
        From Alan Scaife asking Booth to organize the dinner; guest list; invitations; speaker introductions; newspaper photographs and write ups.
    - Inauguration of E.H. Litchfield Committee, 4.
      - Correspondence, minutes, reports, lists of committees, invitations, and schedules, 1955-1957 (Box 7, Folder 120)
        Correspondence - letter stating the terms under which Litchfield agreed to serve as Chancellor, June 29, 1955; members of the inauguration committee appointed; excerpts from letters praising the inauguration ceremonies, October 27, 1955.
        Minutes, 1956.
        Report from Trustees appointed to investigate inaugurations at Yale, Princeton, Columbia and NYU, Inauguration Progress Reports, 1957-1957.
        List of committees for the inauguration, enumeration of committee responsibilities tentative program, 1956-1957.
        Invitations to the seminars on the natural science held in connection with the inauguration, tentative lists of seminar speakers and discussants, December 26, 1956.
        Tentative and final schedule of physical facilities tour; invitation, program.
    - Search Committee for a Successor to E.H. Litchfield, 5.
      - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 121)
        Includes a news release announcing the appointment of a joint faculty trustee search committee, September 14, 1965. The remainder of the correspondence consists of meeting announcements and criteria for choosing a new chancellor; includes "Qualifications Needed by New President of Carnegie Institute of Technology."
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 122)
        Letter listing several candidates and indicating which category they are in, April 4, 1966; 7/28/65 4/6/66 letters nominating and supporting various candidates April and July 1966; Letters to Drs. John T. Wilson, Donald F. Horning, and Dale R. Corson thanking them for coming to Pittsburgh, April 15, 1966; Letters between committee members discussing the qualifications of various candidates; April 26, 1966; Letter from Corson withdrawing his name from consideration; May 25, 1966; Letter from David Truman and letter from Willis Winn withdrawing their names, 1966.
      - Dossiers - Class I candidates (Box 7, Folder 122a)
      - Dossiers - Class II candidates (Box 7, Folder 123)
      - Dossiers - Class III candidates (Box 7, Folder 124)
      - Dossiers - Non-classed candidates (Box 7, Folder 125)
      - Dossiers - Biographical data on candidates (Box 7, Folder 125a)
      - Minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 126)
      - Subject file, January 1966 (Box 7, Folder 127)
        Ford Foundation Report "The University of Pittsburgh: A Selective Review with Proposals for the Future."
      - Subject file (Box 7, Folder 128)
        Chancellor Wesley Posvar's election; letter of recommendation from Henry Heald, consultant to the university.
    - Joint Committee Sessions at Rolling Rock, 6.
      - Minutes, February 18, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - Administrative Committee Sessions at Tumble Run, 7.
      - Minutes, May 19-22, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 130)
      - Reports - Group conferences, July-August 1963 (Box 7, Folder 131)
      - Reports - Group conferences, July-August 1964 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Affiliated University Institutions, 1948-1971; V.
    - Book Center, 1.
      - Subject file, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 133)
        Includes "Book Store News", April 1960; and Issue of Saturday Review containing an article about the Book Store, April 2, 1960.
    - Children's Hospital, 2.
      - Memorandum and annual report, 1953-1972 (Box 8, Folder 134)
        Memorandum of a meeting held in the URA office with the hospital and the university concerning the purchase of land for hospital use, December 2, 1953.
        Children's Hospital Annual Report, 1971/72
    - Falk Clinic, 3.
      - Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 135)
        Concerning the 1928 agreement between the Falk Estate and the University; includes a copy of the agreement.
      - Subject file, 1965-1970 (Box 8, Folder 136)
        "A Report to the Maurice Falk Medical Fund", submitted by the Space Research Coordination Center of the University, April 30, 1965. Ealk Clinic proposed operating budget and capital budget, 1969-1970.
    - Health Center/Medical Center, 4.
      - Correspondence, 1948-1961 (Box 8, Folder 137-142)
        Letter of transmittal regarding the 1948 agreement with Schmidt, Garden, and Erikson architects to become the architects for the Medical Building, 1954; letters regarding solicitation for funds and contracting procedures, August-September 1954; letters transmitting Executive Committee minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1954; letter naming the construction companies to whom bidding materials were sent (Note: the preceding letter to the vice chancellor for the health professions and related correspondence can be found under a letter of transmittal dated, September 2, 1954), August 23, 1954; letter transmitting a summary of the cost for construction, September 20, 1954; letter transmitting a report to building fund subscribers in regards to a report on building progress, October 5, 1954; correspondence regarding construction procedure and acknowledgment of donations, 1954; letter officially appointing the Mellon Stuart Company as prime contractors of the building for the Graduate School of Public Health; 1/27/55, letter transmitting "Procedure on Awarding Sub Contracts "for the health profession schools evaluation of the proposed general contractors, January 27, 1955; numerous letters in regard to contracting procedures and acknowledgment of donations; letter transmitting a statement "Functional Organization, Joint Trustee Committee, University of Pittsburgh Health Center," 1961; in regards to application to the Internal Revenue Service for tax exempt status for the health center hospitals.
      - Financial reports, 1955-1969 (Box 8, Folder 143)
        "Billed Construction Cost at November 1, 1955"; "Tentative Estimates and Potential Source of Funds, October 29, 1958"; Health Center Service Corporation Statement of Income and Expenses, 1968-1969.
      - Minutes, 1941-1970 (Box 8, Folder 144)
      - Memoranda, 1955-1963 (Box 8, Folder 145-146)
        Revised procedure on awarding subcontracts; statements on status, goals, and financial needs of the medical center; resolution concerning laundry service for the health center; "Definition of a University Health Center"; GSA memorandum concerning the proposal to require state aided universities and Medical schools to pay rent on GSA financed projects, July 11, 1963; GSA, statement concerning the proposal to require state aided universities and medical schools to pay rental on GSA financed projects, July 10, 1963; Magee Hospital, resolution to forward a $250,000 grant to the university, December 30, 1955; Statement of current Health Center programs, October 27, 1958.
      - Subject file, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 147)
        Annual Report, 1954/55
      - Subject file, January 27, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 148)
        Articles of Agreement, Health Center Hospitals Campaign, January 27, 1959
        - P-U Hospital, 5.
          - Finance, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 155)
            Capital budget, 1969-1971. Operating budgets, proposed, 1969-1971. New Nuclear Medicine Procedure rates for board approval, September 1, 1971. Statements, financial, April, 1969 also included, letters of transmittal to the finance committee from the executive director explaining changes in the budget.
          - Minutes, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 156-158)
          - Statement of Financial Resources, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 159)
          - Subject file, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 160)
          - Subject file, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 161)
            Regarding reply by a Post-Gazette editorial critical of the hospital's position on the medical staff strike by 1199, 1968-1970. This letter is a statement of the trustees' position, i.e. the reason it refused to hold a representation election. Trustees, lists of members and addresses, 1969-1970.
      - Subject file, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 149)
        Building Fund Committee, regarding organization and solicitation; list of industrial and commercial subscribers, November 18, 1954; revised list of industrial and commercial subscribers, February 7, 1955; and Cornelious M. Smith, "Memorial as a Factor in Fund Raising."
      - Subject file, April 18, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 150)
        Child Guidance Center: Probable Cost and Funds Available for Building; list of gifts, April 18, 1955.
      - Subject file, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 151)
        Fund for the Health Center Hospitals (Brochure), April 28, 1961
      - Subject file, 1954-1965 (Box 8, Folder 152-154)
        Health Center Hospital Service Corporation, Laundry Building First Mortgage Revenue bonds, November 23, 1965; plans for the development of the Health Center, March 1954; proposed contracting procedure for the medical center study committee of the Health Center, report, July 21, 1958; special study committee of the Health Center, preliminary summary and recommendations, June 25, 1958.
    - Western Pennsylvania Psychiatric, 6.
      - House Bill 1482 appropriating money to the university for general maintenance and operation of Western Psychiatric, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 162)
  - Subject Files, 1934-1973; VI.
    - Estate of Edward V. Babcock, 1954; 1.
      - Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 163)
        Letter from Fred Babcock, son of the donor, offering the University the market value of the stock gift instead of the stock itself, October 13, 1954; and correspondence and memoranda which explain this gift.
    - Clapp Hall, 2.
      - Bids (Box 8, Folder 164)
        Proposals by contracting firms: Dick Corporation, Navarro Corporation, O.H. Martin Company, Crump Inc.
      - Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Folder 165)
        Letters concerning cost of construction and construction procedures, i.e. problems and delays; and financial contribution of Mr. and Mrs. William Collin, and Mrs. William Galbraith.
      - Subject file, 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder 166)
        Analysis, points to consider when reading the various bids (breakdown comparisons) of the five bids. Board of Trustees, excerpts from June 8, 1954 minutes indicating acceptance of preliminary drawings, pictures of the exterior of Clapp Hall, front and rear view. Plot plan, blueprint; Schedule of Construction, September 10, 1954. University Building Fund, statement citing the need for a new science building, November 11, 1949.
    - General Correspondence, 3.
      - 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 167)
        - At an informal meeting the Trustees agreed that upon Dr. Bowman's retirement Dr. Fitzgerald, then provost, would become Chancellor, October 9, 1941; 1.
        - Letter to William Wallace Booth from the AAUP stating the organization's philosophy, functions, and goals, March 20, 1944; 2.
        - Letter to William Wallace Booth from the Irish Room Committee urging that an Irish Room be included in the series of Nationality Rooms, July 12, 1944; 3.
        - Letter from the law school dean urging the acceleration of the time required to obtain a law degree to accommodate returning service men, January 31, 1945; 4.
        - Letter relating action of the University Senate heartily approving Dr. Fitzgerald's appointment as chancellor, February 21, 1945; 5.
      - 1946-1950 (Box 8, Folder 168)
        - Efforts by the school of engineering and mines to secure a honorary degree for retiring dean, E.A. Holbrook, July 26, 1947; 1.
        - Notice of a Board of Trustees meeting on December 20 to deal with the question of how to handle 60,000 shares of Gulf Oil stock donated by the A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust, December 16, 1948; 2.
      - 1951-1955 (Box 8, Folder 169)
        - Negotiations concerning purchase of the Masonic Temple and Masonic Temple Property, October 5, 1951; 1.
        - $15,000 to the Metallurgical Engineering Department to establish a Research Professorship in Blast Furnace Technology, December 5, 1952; 2.
        - Summary of proposed by law changes, March 2, 1953; 3.
        - Luncheon honoring E.H. Litchfield the Dean of the School of Business and Public Affairs at Cornell. The purpose of Litchfield's visit was to acquaint him with the university, May 16, 1955; 4.
        - Letter in regards to the dinner honoring retiring Chancellor Fitzgerald, June 1955; 5.
        - Housing for the chancellor, October 27, 1955; 6.
      - 1956-1962 (Box 8, Folder 170)
        - Tax exempt status of faculty club dues, 1958-1962; 1.
        - Letter written by Chancellor Litchfield extolling year around education, 2.
      - 1963-1969 (Box 8, Folder 171)
        - Letter to the Board of Trustees from Trustee Emil Narick, whose term as a trustee was about to expire, calling for the Trustees to exercise greater leadership and suggesting that Pitt become a public(state related) institution serving the people of Western Pennsylvania, May 12, 1965; 1.
        - Letter from Dr. Litchfield to William Wallace Booth asking the latter to convoy his resignation to the Board of Trustees. Also included is Litchfield's statement to the press, July 1965; 2.
        - Letter to the GSA regarding whether the GSA will fund the acquisition of the cemetery belonging to the First Trinity Evangelical Lutheran Church of Pittsburgh, March 8, 1966; 3.
        - Success in raising the first installment to match a $20,000 grant from the Ford Foundation for the Graduate School of Business Administration, August 19, 1966; 4.
        - Letter from W.W. Posvar stating his reasons for requesting that the Trustees postpone redecorating the Chancellor's home, April 4, 1967; 5.
        - University funding of fraternity housing, September 8, 1969; 6.
    - General Alumni Association, 4.
      - Alumni Giving Fund, 1949-1961 (Box 8, Folder 172)
      - Alumni Fund Board of Directors minutes, November 8, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 173)
        Minutes of meeting where the creation of the board was discussed; memoranda concerning "New Concepts in Alumni Campaigning" list of prospective board members; director's meeting minutes, November 8, 1966.
      - Alumni Giving Fund Newsletter, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 174)
      - Correspondence, 1934-1939 (Box 8, Folder 175)
        Letters in regards to solicitation of new members for the GSA, 1939; and letter appointing Booth to the Alumni Council.
      - Correspondence, February-August 1940 (Box 8, Folder 176)
        All the correspondence in this folder relates to the Alumni representation plan.
      - Correspondence, September 1940-March 1941 (Box 8, Folder 177)
      - Correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 178)
        For the most part these letters are notices of council meetings, appointments, and resolutions.
      - Correspondence, 1946-1950 (Box 8, Folder 179)
        Includes amongst other letters: May 29, 1946, letter to members of the Alumni council stating plans to revitalize the GSA. August 24, 1946, letter stating that William Wallace Booth had been appointed to the Alumni Fund Committee; also noting the publication of the new Pitt Alumni News Review. March 25, 1947, brief biographical sketch of William Wallace Booth. June 26, 1947, letter to William Wallace Booth announcing the organization of the alumni giving fund and outlining the principles upon which fund raising campaigns will be conducted. May 4, 1950, letter announcing the results of balloting for alumni trustee, and noting that William Wallace Booth was not renominated. November 14, 1950, regarding space for fraternities in the new dormitories.
      - Correspondence, 1951-1960 (Box 8, Folder 180)
        Includes amongst other letters: February 19, 1952, letter noting the launching of the Century Club. 1955, correspondence in regards to a suitable building for the Alumni House. November 19, 1955, notice of the creation of a new committee known as the Bequest Committee.
      - Financial statements, 1939-1946 (Box 8, Folder 181)
      - Memoranda in regard to the Alumni Representation Plan (Box 8, Folder 182)
      - Minutes, 1939-1945 (Box 8, Folder 183)
      - Minutes, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 184)
      - Minutes, 1950-1953 (Box 8, Folder 185)
      - Subject file - Alumni Membership Council, 1947-1953 (Box 8, Folder 186)
      - Subject file - Alumni Giving Fund, 1940-1965 (Box 8, Folder 187)
      - Subject file - Biographical sketches of nominees for Alumni Trustees including the plan of electing alumni trustee, 1940-1965 (Box 8, Folder 188)
      - Subject file - By-laws of the General Alumni Association, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 189)
      - Subject file - Charter memoranda concerning a new charter for the university, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 190)
      - Subject file - Chemistry Department newsletter and a biographical sketch of the department chairman, Alexander Silverman, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 191)
      - Subject file - Miscellaneous, 1940-1963 (Box 8, Folder 192-193)
        Proposed amendments to the election procedure for alumni trustees, 1963. Report and analysis of the report of the Temporary Committee to study the athletic situation, 1948. Report on Legal Education in Pittsburgh, Lon 1. Fuller, Harvard, 1951 (Excerpts). Proposed Constitution of the Allegheny College Alumni, 1952. Pamphlet "The Work of the GAA", Pitt, undated. Memorandum on proposed trophy competition, 1953. Press release regarding alumni representative plan, December 26, 1940. School of Applied Social Science, proposed constitution, 1943.
    - Donation to the University of the Heinz Estate, 5.
      - Correspondence, document, petition, photograph, and maps, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 194)
        Correspondence - Regarding the application to the City Planning Commission for a certificate of Occupancy; April 8, 1953, letter to the planning Committee requesting a change in zoning so the University can use the property; May 26, 1953, in regards to the University desire to sell the property.
        Document - Board of Adjustment, denial of request to change zoning because only council can admit such a variance to the zoning laws.
        Petition - A statement to be signed by residence of Morewood Avenue consenting to the requested zoning variance. Includes a statement of how Pitt intended to use the property.
        Photograph - H.J. Heinz Estate, March 17, 1953.
        Maps - Indicating location of the property.
    - Law School Class of 1922, 6.
      - Correspondence regarding Booth's appointment as class secretary to contact class of 1922 member, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 195)
      - Reunion, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 196)
      - Reunion, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 197)
      - Reunion, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 198)
      - Reunion, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 199)
      - Reunion, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 200)
      - Reunion, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 201)
    - Chancellor E.H. Litchfield, 7.
      - Correspondence and speeches, 1959-1965 (Box 9, Folder 202)
        Correspondence: October 17, 1959, letter to an alumnus explaining what percentage of the budget goes to football and stating that the football program is a necessary part of the university. April 29, 1965, form letter drawn up by the Chancellor to be sent to various corporations for solicitation.
        Speeches: "Voluntary Action and the Modern Corporations" to the Chambers of Commerce of the US, May 21, 1960. Remarks at the ground breaking ceremonies for the physical education building, August 26, 1960. Opening Commencement remarks, June 11, 1962.
    - Memoranda, 8.
      - 1963-1967 (Box 9, Folder 203)
        - Bequest of William H. Allison, April 20, 1967; 1.
        - Bank loan (temporary) for purchase of property for which anticipated allocations have not been received, 2.
        - Acquisition of the Casey residence at 4130 Bigelow by the University, July 9, 1963; 3.
        - Concern over cost of Chancellor's residence renovation, April 6,1967; 4.
        - "The Changing Role of the University of Pittsburgh," no author, 5.